A Guide to the Wayne L. Dernoncourt Papers, 1950-1980
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Wayne L. Dernoncourt Papers, 1950-1980
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1988-025
0.5 cu. ft. 1 box
Papers of Textile Workers Union of America vice president Wayne Dernoncourt, including circular letters, printed materials, memorabilia, and photographs.
Dernoncourt, Wayne L.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Wayne L. Dernoncourt Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1988.
Biographical/Historical Note
Wayne LeRoi Dernoncourt, a union organizer and official in the Textile Workers Union of America, was born in Springfield, Illinois, on June 15, 1918. He was the son of Joseph Dernoncourt, himself a union organizer, and Amelia Dernoncourt. Starting work while still a minor, Dernoncourt soon became involved in union organization, serving on the Steel Workers Organizing Committee during the 1930s. Dernoncourt married Leona Lambeseder (1920-1996), and the couple would have three children. After serving in the U. S. Army during World War II, Dernoncourt joined the staff of the Textile Workers Union of America (TWUA) in February 1946. He became a vice-president of the union in 1964. When the TWUA merged with the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America in 1976, becoming the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, Dernoncourt was named vice-president and director of the Upper South Region of the Textile Division. He co-authored The Grievance Procedure and Arbitration: Text and Cases (Washington: University Press of America, 1978). In his later years, Dernoncourt lived in Lynchburg, Virginia, where he died on March 16, 1981.
The Textile Workers Union of America (TWUA) was formed in 1939 through a merger of the Textile Workers Organizing Committee and the United Textile Workers. As part of the Congress of Industrial Relations (CIO), the TWUA participated in the CIO's push to unionize industries in the American South. Beginning in 1948, the union became embroiled in bitter infighting between factions led by the union's president, Emil Rieve, and its executive vice-president, George Baldanzi. The 1952 biennial convention was particularly contentious and led to the secession of Baldanzi and his faction to the rival United Textile Workers (UTW). A number of TWUA locals followed Baldanzi to the UTW, resulting in a loss of 50,000 TWUA members. In 1976, the TWUA merged with the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America to form the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU). The new union had an initial membership of approximately 500,000, but it shrank steadily in the following decades. In 1995, the ACTWU merged with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, becoming the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). In 2004, UNITE in turn merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) to form UNITE HERE.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of Wayne L. Dernoncourt, a union organizer and official in the Textile Workers Union of America (TWUA). Included are circular letters, reports, speech texts, printed materials, memorabilia, and photographs. Much of the material in the collection (especially the circular letters and printed material) focuses on 1950s infighting within the TWUA between factions headed by TWUA executive vice-president George Baldanzi and president Emil Rieve. The collection also holds materials distributed at the 1980 International Foundation of Employee Benefit Plans Educational Conference and a folder of material associated with a LaSalle Extension University law course taken by Dernoncourt. A small assortment of memorabilia and photographs, the majority of both relating to the TWUA, completes the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type, then chronologically.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Labor unions
Contents List
- Circular letters, 1950-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1-2)
- Speech texts, 1951, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
- "Virginia State AFL-CIO's Program of Progress for Virginia," [1963?] (Box-folder 1-4)
- Broadsides and articles, 1952-1956, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
- Booklets, 1952-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - "Convention Songs," 1952
  - "Structure Committee Report Submitted to the TWUA Executive Council at Its Pre-Convention Meeting," 1952
  - Rules Committee Report Submitted to the TWUA Seventh Biennial Convention," 1952
  - "Two Years of Aggression: a Documentary Record of Baldanzi's Campaign to Take Over TWUA," [1952]
  - "Constitutional Amendments Supported by the Pre-Convention Committee for a Democratic TWUA," [1952]
  - "'I Salute You, Gabe...' For Exposing the Baldanzi-Baron Plan to Take Over TWUA--or Split It," [1952]
  - "The Morristown Story" by William Michael Goldsmith, [1952]
  - "The True Story of TWUA in Dixie," [1952?]
  - "Mariano S. Bishop," 1954
  - "Ethical Practices Code of the Textile Workers Union of America AFL-CIO," 1957
  - Converse, South Carolina TWUA Local 325 union hall dedication, [1957]
  - "United and Progress Through Democracy: the Program of the Pre-Convention Committee for a Democratic TWUA," n.d.
- International Foundation of Employee Benefit Plans Educational Conference, 1980, [3 folders] (Box-folder 1-7)
- LaSalle Extension University American law and procedure course, 1952, n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
- Memorabilia, 1952-1973, n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
  - TWUA local 6 (Lewistown, Pennsylvania) license plate, n.d.
  - TWUA convention medals and ribbons, 1952-1958, [2 items]
  - "Support Rieve Administration" badge, n.d.
  - "Unity and Progress Through Democracy" badge, n.d.
  - International Date Line certificate of crossing, 1973, [2 items]
- Photographs, 1952-1965, n.d., [20 items] (Box-folder 1-10)
  - TWUA convention (Cleveland, Ohio), 1952, [2 items]
  - TWUA convention (Atlantic City, New Jersey), 1954
  - TWUA convention (New York City), 1964
  - TWUA Local 325 (Converse, South Carolina) union hall dedication, [1957], [3 items]
  - Unidentified groups, n.d., [2 items]
  - Snapshots, 1960-1965, n.d., [11 items]